A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Chronological Files, Series 2 FA815
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Chronological Files, Series 2
1969-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Seitz, Frederick
FA815
8.74 Cubic Feet 23 letter document boxes
Biographical/Historical note
Frederick Seitz (b. July 4, 1911) is a physicist and science administrator. He has made fundamental contributions to the theory of solids, nuclear physics, fluorescence, and crystals, and has been a leader in the post - World War II scientific establishment in the United States. From 1968-1978 Seitz was president of the Rockefeller University.
Seitz entered Stanford University in January 1929, where he started out as a biochemistry major, but soon focused on mathematics and physics. He graduated from Stanford in three years with a degree in mathematics, and started doctoral studies in physics at Princeton University at the beginning of 1932. Completing his doctorate in 1934 Seitz remained at Princeton as a Proctor Fellow, and in 1935 was appointed as an instructor at the University of Rochester. In 1939 Seitz moved to the University of Pennsylvania first as assistant professor, 1939-1941, and then associate professor, 1941-1942, in the Morgan Laboratory of Physics. Seitz moved to the University of Illinois in 1949 to accept an appointment as a professor of Physics. In the 40s and 50s Seitz's research focused on the properties of crystals. His published works included studies of dislocations and imperfections in crystal structures, the effect of irradiation on crystals, and the process of diffusion in crystalline materials. In 1962 Seitz was elected president of the National Academy of Sciences in Washington, a position which he held for 6 years. In that same year, he became a trustee of the Rockefeller University and in 1968 he went on to become president of the Rockefeller University. In 1973 he received the National Medal of Science, the nation's highest award in science, for his contributions "to the foundation of the modern quantum theory of the solid state of matter."
Among his numerous honors and awards, Dr. Seitz received the Franklin Medal in 1965, the Herbert Hoover Medal in 1968, the Defense Department Distinguished Service Award in Awards in 1968, the NASA distinguished Service in 1969, the Compton Award, the highest award of the American Institute of Physics, in 1970, and the James Madison Medal of Princeton University in 1978. In 1979 he received his second NASA Distinguished Public Service Medal presented for his "dedicated service as chairman of the NASA Space Program Advisory Council from 1973 to 1977. " In addition to the Rockefeller University, 26 universities in this country and abroad have awarded him honorary degrees. In 1983 he received the Fourth Vannevar Bush Award presented by the National Science Board of the National Science Foundation and the R. Loveland Memorial Award of the American College of Physicians. From 1978 to 1983 he served as vice chairman of the Board of Trustees of the Memorial Sloan - Kettering Cancer Center.
Other memberships include the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, The Century Club, the Bohemian Club, the American Philosophical Society, the American Society for Metals, the American Institute of Mining, Metallurgy and Petroleum Engineers, the American Crystallographic Society, the Optical Society of America, the Washington Academy of Science, and a number of European scientific academies.
Other Finding Aids
FA141 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Business, Series 1. FA816 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Archive Center, Series 3. FA817 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Campus, Series 4. FA818 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, General Administration, Series 5. FA819 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Personal, Biographical and Miscellaneous, Series 6.
Arrangement note
Collection is arranged in six series: 1. Business, 1929-1979 2. Chronological Files, 1969-1978 3. Archive Center, 1971-1977 4. Campus, 1968-1978 5. General Administration, 1958-1979 6. Presonal, Biographical and Misccellaneous, 1951-1968.
Arrangement mainly alphabetical and chronological by series.
File Plan note
Former Classification: 1 304-2
Conditions Governing Access note
Records more than 25 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Contains chronological files.
Physical sciences; New York (N.Y.); Urban policy -- New York (State) -- New York; Physics; Regional planning -- New York (N.Y.); Operations management; Biology -- Research
- Chronological Files, 1969-1978; 2; 10.12 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes Outgoing Correspondence.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Chronological File, 1969 April-June (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological File, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File, 1969 August-September 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1969 September 12-30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1969 October-November 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1969 November-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1970 January (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chronological File, 1970 February (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File, 1970 March (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1970 April (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1970 May (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1970 June (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1970 July-August (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chronological File, 1970 September (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Chronological File, 1970 October (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Chronological File, 1970 November (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File, 1970 December (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1971 January (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1971 February (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1971 March (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1971 April (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chronological File, 1971 May (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chronological File, 1971 June (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File, 1971 July (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1971 August (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1971 September (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1971 October (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1971 November (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Chronological File, 1971 December (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Chronological File, 1972 January (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chronological File, 1972 February (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File, 1972 March (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1972 April (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1972 May (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1972 June (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1972 July (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Chronological File, 1972 August (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File, 1972 September (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1972 October (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1972 November (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1972 December (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1973 January (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Chronological File, 1973 February (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Chronological File, 1973 March (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File, 1973 April (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1973 May (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1973 June (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1973 July (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1973 August (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Chronological File, 1973 September (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File (1), 1973 October (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File (2), 1973 October (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1973 November (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1973 December (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1974 January (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Chronological File, 1974 February (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Chronological File, 1974 March (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File, 1974 April (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1974 May (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1974 June (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Chronological File, 1974 July (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Chronological File, 1974 August (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Chronological File, 1974 September (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Chronological File, 1974 October (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Chronological File, 1974 November (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Chronological File, 1974 December (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 January 2-14 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 January 15-22 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 January 23-31 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 February 3-13 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 February 14-28 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 March 4-23 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 March 24-31 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 April 1-7 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 April 8-17 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 April 21-30 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 May 1-8 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 May 9-20 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 May 21-31 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 June 2-17 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 June 18-30 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 July 1-14 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 July 15-30 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 August 4-22 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 August 25-29 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 September 2-12 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 September 15-30 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 October 1-14 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 October 15-22 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 October 23-31 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 November 4-12 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 November 13-24 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 November 26 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 December 1-9 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1975 December 10-23 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 January 6-16 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 January 19-29 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 February 2-10 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 February 11-19 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 February 20-27 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 March 1-15 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 March 16-19 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 March 22-30 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 April 1-9 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 April 12-19 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 April 20-30 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 May 3-6 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 May 7-17 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 May 18-27 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 June 1-11 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 June 14-30 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 July 1-8 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 July 9-23 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 July 26-30 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 August 1-10 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 August 11-31 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 September 1-8 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 September 8-13 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 September 15-23 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 September 29-30 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 October 1-8 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 October 12-20 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 October 21-29 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 November 1-3 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 November 4-16 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 November 17-19 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 November 20-30 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 December 1-7 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1976 December 8-30 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 January 3-10 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 January 11-21 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 January 24-31 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 February 1-8 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 February 8-15 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 February 16-28 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 March 1-4 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 March 7-15 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 March 16-31 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 April 1-14 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 April 5-25 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 April 26-29 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 May (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 June 1-6 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 June 7-16 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 June 17-30 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 July 1-14 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 July 22-28 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 August 1-16 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 August 17-22 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 August 23-31 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 September 1-14 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 September 15-30 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 October 3-12 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 October 13-20 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 October 21-31 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 November 1-7 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 November 10-15 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 November 16-30 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 December 1-13 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 December 14-20 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1977 December 21-30 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 January 3-11 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 January 12-23 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 January 24-31 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 February 1-17 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 February 20-28 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 March 1-6 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 March 7-14 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 March 15-31 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 April 3-17 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 April 18-28 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 May 1-9 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 May 10-30 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 June 1-9 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1978 June 7-22 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Alberico-Bardossi (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Bayless (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Berlin-Broadbent (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Campo, Anthony J. (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Carmichael, Ray F. (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Contes, Z. (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Dana, R., 1 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Dana, R., 2 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Dana, R., 3 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Dress-Garvey (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Gold, 1 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Gold, 2 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Gold, 3 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Harrar (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Hirsch, James G. (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Hubbard-Jordan (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Kappas (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Kone (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Luckey (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Lyons, 1 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Lyons, 2 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Lyons, 3 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, Lyons, 4 (Box 23, Folder 4)